All right. Hello guys. Good morning,
good afternoon, good evening. Welcome to
another episode of talk show. We are
going to code F and JavaScript. Kind of
random. Okay, I'm just doing my regular
talk show. I'm a programming nerd since
and uh you know I'm gonna talk about
basically the mainstream
uh point of view that's what I am okay
so you're looking at me my keyboard uh
this is ultimate hacking keyboard I have
a review on YouTube and newly track ball
uh so let's show
the uh my screen. Okay, so 1,000
articles. So if you're here, say hi.
Love to see your comments. Hello sis
Piri. Hello. Is F the new goat?
Uh Zuma jargon warning. Yes, F is the
new goat. Uh in fact, I discovered in
the past few years, I discovered that in
fact F is the best language. Okay. So I
talked about this a thousand times. Let
me explain one more time. Just one
minute. So F came from O camel. It's a
derivative kind of or camel. Okamo came
from camel. Camel came from ML. So camel
ML which stand for meta language. So in
the 1970s there is this language ML meta
language.
Then it has kind of variations. Then you
got SML for standard ML. Then you got
camel
at um you know camel which stand for
anyway camel. Okay. Then or camel. Then
Microsoft made F out of it around the
year 2005. Okay. So all these languages
are basically the same effectively the
same. Today they also have JavaScript
versions like basically the Okamo
language but in JavaScript syntax by
face by by the guy who created React.
Okay, this a so you [snorts] search for
ML script or recript re um
okay let's uh let's digress okay so I'm
talking about okamo so and let me tell
you why okay so uh rescript okay so
let's some basic information okay so
rescript is the script programming
language which is basically okamo but in
javascript syntax Okay, they made it and
Okay, so rescript.
Okay, so uh fantastic and I want to show
you. Okay, so um Okamel uh well I don't
need to show. So anyway, Okamo. Okay, so
you can read Wikipedia and F. Okay, so
basically they are the same family. So
I've been reading you know so I first
heard of it since 1990s
along with Hascal and back then there's
Miranda there's hope there's clean
several like today you wouldn't know so
those are functional programming
languages you can still see some of them
mentioned here so for example uh no none
of them here so anyway there's Miranda
hope Miranda and hope and so anyway in
the 1990s 1990s. So there's so camel.
Okay. So camel and ML camel you know
they are the same thing. So the first
one is ML which stand for meta language.
Okay. Uh it began in 1973.
Okay. By by this guy Robin Miller. Okay.
This
okay. So I want to tell you in the past
few years my study of programming
languages I realized oh this ML is
actually so basically
we had the best programming language
beginning in 1973
like it would be it's the best okay it's
the best programming language and we
kind of already know the technology why
you know since 1973
so we don't need C, C car or today's
Rust. Actually, we don't need none of
it. We don't need Golang. We don't need
Scala. We don't need Java. Okay, this
this ML and later on Okamo Okamo being
the most famous because they made the
most best implementation and fast.
And Okamo is very fast. Okay, it's you
know compared to C maybe a bit slower
but it's super fast and it's got auto
memory management so-called garbage
collection. Okay. So anyway in my
programming language studies I realized
truly ML from 1970 that at that time we
already have the best uh programming
language and the most important
technology in ML is this uh
hinder mind
hinderly ma type system. Okay, that is a
basically that's a type inference. You
may may heard of it from Haskell or
today in Golan in Rust in basically all
modern languages automatic type
inference. Okay,
because back then when C, you know,
during the C time 1970s, these idiots,
these C and C, PPP, C++ idiots, they
have types, you know, strongly typed
programming languages. Uh, but their
type is for the computer. It's like you
know when you create a variable let's
say x equals to three a number or x
equals to uh john a name a string
why do you have to declare what type of
it is it why do you have to you know
when when I give a value x= to 3 or x=
to john a string you know the machine
should know Why do I have to say, "Oh,
by by the way, I'm going to begin to use
this variable named X, and by the way,
uh, I intend to use this X as a number."
It's a idiocy. Okay, that's a C
and C++ idiots.
Now, when these people begin, of course,
they they don't think it that way. They
just thought, you know, you need to
implement it, but it's the most easy to
have the programmer tell it, you know.
So [laughter]
you know implementation into bits you
know so that's that's that's what they
that's what they did okay so no now you
now you have to remember back then it's
not like today you got internet you got
AI you can you can ask oh uh are there
other languages that has this character
uh you know you can there's no
information like that
no no no internet no Wikipedia the only
way you have to be like a PhD student uh
one of the you know scientist
working with a handful other scientist
you know and anything you don't know you
have to read other scientists research
paper okay to know other languages you
know that's oh what what you know oh
there's another language you know you
have to read research papers or journals
or sometimes books you you don't have
like information like today Wikipedia
you know so when see creators you know
created they they might have heard of ML
but they don't know like they you know
they are it's not like today oh you know
it's it's easily connected I can talk to
any one of you right okay so anyway the
so that's this is my thoughts okay so in
1970s we got this hinderly mona type
system and what is ML meta language for
it is designed to do mathematical
proofs.
Okay. Uh this LCF theorem prover. Okay.
I started to know more about it. Today
you got ling l ean which I intend to
master this year. Okay. So anyway you
got so so anyway so this you got this
ML. So it turns out and and starting
with you know so it's in academia. So
back then ML
the uh Robin Miller this this amazing
guy he's a student of of the lisp
creator um uh John McCarthy okay John
McCarthy is from 1960s he created lisp
which is based on lambda calculus so so
so is ML okay but Rob Robbie Miller is a
I think student or re research
um assistant or some some some kind of
employee of the of the lisp
creator um John McCarthy. Okay. So John
McCarthy is creating you know created
this it has lots of features we use
today automatic memory management the
concept of error handling exceptions
um the functional programming also from
lisp okay uh functional programming
automatic memory management
uh functional programming and uh
symbolic computation you you deal with
symbols. Okay, symbolic computation and
uh um and auto memory management we
already mentioned and exceptions. Okay,
quite a few. I have an article on that.
So you can so so this so basically the
most important programming language
features came from lisp. Okay, not C and
C++
Okay. So, so and and then and the ML
this guy Robin Miller is a student of of
John or something. So, I mean but so
they he created ML and originally a lot
of this is implemented in this. Okay.
So, it says here you see ML started
development by Robin Maer upon his
arrival at University of Edinburg.
Edinburg with a with a help of research
assistant Lockwood Maurice and something
something both postocs from Stanford who
were hired by Mona. Okay. Uh but then
you can see the connection to Lisp to
John uh McCarthy
because you know I I know about ML. I
mean I heard of it. So but I was
wondering what why is there no
connection to Lisp? Because back then
lisp is a big thing. Then I asked AI
then AI started to tell me that actually
they are very much connected. I mean
they they they don't mesh that much but
they but the ML guy is from the um the
list creator group. Okay they you know
they are researching on mathematical
proof systems and artificial
intelligence. Okay. Anyway, I digressed,
you know, I digressed into a little bit
history, but I realized really this ML
language is really from 1970s, we
already have the best programming
language
together with the lisp invention of
interpreted programming language. Okay,
there's another thing. So um me
automatic memory management
symbolic computation functional
programming exception exceptions in in
interpreter like you have command
command line okay you don't have you
know this this is created by lisp
you know like cd
cd web [laughter]
command line, you know, let's say let's
say let's start Python 3 + 2 repo. The
idiot the the the the idiots
call it ripple. Okay, this this
interactive command line interface came
from lisp. Okay, so if you think about
it, today's programming language
technology, most of it like like the
most important thing came from lisp.
interpreter, automemory management,
functional programming, symbolic
computation
and this this ripple okay command line
interactive interactive
interface
like you don't have to oh no I need to
compile and linker and
so then so so so this Stanford group you
know so one of the student or something
I forgot what's the connection but you
can you can easily read it you know
connection of ML robing ma and the the
John McCarthy.
So they are like you know so they so so
ML I now I realized is just like the
best programming language we have it
since 1970s and the most important thing
about this ML family is this
hint uh Hindley Mner type system
basically it means automatic type
inference. Okay, th this thing this
thing is amazing. You know, today is any
new new language since 10 years ago have
this. Okay, this from 1970s and and this
thing uh this actually became this thing
actually became the foundation of type
theory or proof theory like uh for
foundation of mathematics. This this
because anything you can compute that
means it's proven. Okay, essentially
that's what it means
by by this kind of type inference. Okay,
so this amazing and this this strongly
typed you know so-called today we call
it oh strongly type statically type
programming language like Java, C, C++
but their their type is is entirely
different from this type inference. the
C and C++ idiots in Java layer type is
like for the machine you know so so it's
easier to implement you know oh by the
way you know if you're going to use a
variable you better say what type it is
so we can recall so it's easier to
implement you see that that's strongly
typed programming languages C++ Java but
this thing it is also you know the
Haskell ML or camel f is also strongly
type, but it's that it's not a
for the machine. It's this is this is
from mathematics and it's it's got auto
automatic type inference.
It's amazing. Okay. And and and it's not
just recording of oh what what what bits
you know like string type or the number
how many int how many short you know
long float the i e e you know 545
something you can have it's not about
that this type this this type strongly
typed in Haskell in ML in or camel in F
it's about
the ma you know the the type you want
the the mathematical types. Okay, it's
not about the int and flow. So it's
quite amazing.
So that so so that's what I want to tell
you. In the past few years, you know, in
my study of programming language, I just
I just realized this ML thing is is
that's just amazing. Okay, it's just
amazing.
Uh yeah,
and uh you know, so I you know, I
despise CC and CPP. They are the worst
crap possible. Plus, they got a code.
Anyway, so I digressed over. So I I was
going to do some um I wanted I wanted to
tell you these uh computer languages
characters frequency, okay? which I
wrote in Typescript in JavaScript. So
you can tell what punctuation characters
is most most frequently used. So for
example, you got um so you can see in
JavaScript the equal sign is most most
frequently used. You know you can you
have statistics for Java JavaScript for
Java for Java it's a dot and paren and
semicolon. For Golan it's the dot and
paren and comma. Okay, you see very
different languages they have different
frequency of the the punctuations.
Now for C++ it's a low line or also
known as underscore because every name
you know C++ you have to use that which
came from C. So for C and C++ the
underscore character is the most
frequently used.
Then in C++ after that it's a slash.
Okay, I don't know C++. Why why is slash
used uh so frequently? Because of the
name space or something separator. Okay,
then for PHP it's a dollar sign and
apostrophe. For Python, it's the
underscore just like C and dot and
apostrophe and parn. Okay, so in Ruby
it's a underscore again. Pearl it's a
dollar sign bash. So anyway so uh then
you got CSS you got wam language then
you got emacis of course parent and
hyphen because in eac list every every
function name you use hyphen. Okay just
like CSS.
So anyway so so this this is
interactive. So you can uh for example
here is uh you can type anything
delete it type
anything you want and it
became a graph of frequency. Okay and
you can make it just show punctuation
only. So uh merge case no Chinese top 30
showed uh no English alphabet there. So
now it's empty. Now you need to add some
punctuation. So if I go to some code,
let's go to some code
JavaScript. Okay. So uh let's say okay
copy that. Okay. This is uh some
TypeScript. Let's go here and select or
paste. So you can see this is
TypeScript, you know, some short
TypeScript code. So anyway, so this is
useful. So, I hope you guys like it. So,
let me post the URL.
And I want to add uh F and C to my
collection because I don't think uh
because I don't have it there.
Okay. I'm going to read a comment in a
second. Okay. Unicode F close uh talk
show. Yeah. So, I want to add
FS
and C for this. Okay. And the other
thing I wanted to do, yeah, I wanted to
um I want to
uh with AI help, I'm going to write a
script like how do you call a shell
command in Fle
often when when you do um
you know scripting you know C admin or
often you need to call shell script for
example convert png ng images or JPEG
images to WEBP format which I I talked
about I've done
in uh last month or two live stream. So
you have to convert hundreds or
thousands of PNG to JPEG or to to WEBP
format. So you need to call uh the shell
command webp C webp.
So but if you need you you know so so
you how do you call a shell command from
F? That's what I want to know. Okay, so
that's one thing uh I was planning to
do.
Then there's another thing about
JavaScript mini minifi. Okay, so but
maybe not today. So let me see the
comments. Okay. Um so let's see
comments. Uh so yeah so I find F
tremendous you know of course but the
there's one thing about
programming languages they are not
governed you know the popularity of
programming languages is not governed by
the how technically how good it is but
rather it's mostly by social forces okay
social forces for example the most
popular languages we use C C++ first,
JavaScript, PHP,
and Python, they tends to be the worst
now. Especially
C uh C++,
PHP, JavaScript. They are they are like
the worst but they became the most
dominant popular programming language.
And second to those, I would say C also
very bad. Python also not so good. Okay.
But the the good ones like like F or
camel
or they are not that much used you know.
Okay. But so that comes to rust you
know. So you know I did a live stream
installing rust. Um right I can show
you. So I can for example let's turn
let's go to stop stop stop stop stop
stop stop stop stop stop stop stop stop
stop the python um control uh control z
what exit now stupid python
exit okay so gcm ro c okay so you see I
got rust installed
so why am I learning rust because it's
amazing because I'm into functional
programming my first programming
language for seven years is wufam
language starting in 1993.
My first programming language wam. Okay,
that's why I talk about wuam uh very
often. This thing this this this this
thing is amazing. This this wra language
is a magnitude more high level than all
programming languages. A magnitude not
just a little bit. Like today you
consider Python you know oh my god
Python uh Python machine learning
libraries 2 gigabyte
you know Google's you know machine
learning pi sci numpy you know oh you
can do linear algebra oh integral oh
python you know the 4 gabyte or
python whatever combined is like it's is
like trivial I mean so wuam language is
like a magnitude can you can do more
than than than the entire 4 gigabyte of
whatever Google's machine learning added
or or math into Python. That's amazing
you know wam language and it's in one
coherent thing and wam language is
basically
lisp it's a symbolic just like lisp so
you can think of it as a family of lisp
lisp and uh apl
you know if you don't know it's kind of
like a so-called array languages so that
means
many values are just a matrix okay
instead of just one single value you
deal with matrixes you can okay often so
many functions automatically apply to to
the argument which is a matrix so it
apply to all arguments anyway that's
called array languages okay but wuam
languages is more than that it's a you
know it's a
computer algebra system besides that
so this this you know so my first
language is wuang language for seven
years then I started to learn Oh, Unix.
Interesting. Oh, [laughter]
what what is Unix? So, so attractive,
you know. You you you know, you got this
coat culture, you know. Oh, grab, you
know, what what is grab grab and t
[laughter]
I started to learn and pearl, you know,
the the Swiss army knife, you know,
pearl. Oh, pearl. I started to learn and
then then I started to see why are these
languages so extreme idiotic I
don't understand
then I started to know about oh C and
C++ [laughter] it's worse and Java okay
then then after probably my I learned
some Java you know it's so so
one line of wam language is 100 lines of
Java like you have to declare class in
this clear um variable like type and
stuff like what what the is going
on you know. [laughter]
So for example to open a file just say
open file path in wra language you know
but then but in Java oh you need a uh
file object then you need a file handler
something object you need then you need
a text stream object you have to
[laughter]
extreme idiocy
but you see 30 years ago I don't know
much about you know all other
programming languages or why things are
that way I the only thing I know is wam
language I read the you know this thick
manual thousand pages multiple time
times that's how I mastered it but I
don't know you know C or Java why are
they there why are so you know like
industrial programming language why not
many people use wuan
uh you know like why why why why is this
all perl
you know what what is networking I don't
know what is operating system I don't
know right so but now I know of course I
know I have you know overview of the
computer computing industry and and
computer um computer science okay that's
separate things computer science then
computer engineering and computer
industry you know the industry practices
you know and so on so today I kind of
see So wam language turns out it's the
it's like a highest level programming
language by a magnitude
[laughter] and that's my first language.
So
that obviously I'm not going to like C,
C++ or Java this and and they are just
idiotic then you know
you know and and this woofer language is
a in in terms of computer science it's a
term rewriting system it's not like the
you know typical other programming like
JavaScript or Java or Pearl or Python or
C or C++ plus+ none of it. This is this
is you got a term rewriting system
in terms of symbolic expressions like
lisp but lisp is not a term rewriting
system you got a term rewriting system
here
you know I've done many wam language um
coding in the past hundreds of them so
you can watch uh the last you know this
year it's not so good but you can watch
my older ones you can search on my
website you you'll find you know hundred
hundreds of articles
So that's you know so so basically when
you are about
you know I I you know a lot of you guys
are young you know teen or something but
so when you reach 30 years old 40 years
old for or me 50 60 you look back then
you realized what's going on um you know
what you know all the questions you had
so now I kind of know why you know why
is it this way or that way or things
like that. So why is C popular C++?
Well, [laughter]
[gasps]
social reasons. Okay, many social
reasons and many of them not very good
because we end up with PHP and
JavaScript. That's the worst
possible and C++ like the worst
possible because social forces because
corporations they want to make money.
Nobody cares about oh this is the great
technology they everyone every person in
down to every one of us we are here just
trying to make money to to to make the
maximum out of for benefit just yourself
okay so all the corporation they do that
and we end up with PHP JavaScript
and C++
okay that's how things are the different
forces okay not because oh C++ of the
problem. No, you know, like for example,
JavaScript, why why are we stuck with
JavaScript? Can the browser, for
example, browsers,
Firefox, Google, this, you know, mega
corporate, especially Google, mega
corporation, they they they got billions
and billions of dollars. Why can't they
say, "Hey, hey, browser guys, come, you
know, let's stop JavaScript. Let's just
create a new language, clean, start from
scratch. I'm the boss. I got billions of
dollars. Let's we, you know, let's do
this together and we don't have to deal
with the extreme of JavaScript
anymore. Can they do that? Sure. Sure.
But that's like ideal, but who's going
to do that? You know, it doesn't work
that way.
So that's my um
that's kind of my perspective on
programming languages, the popularity
and stuff and why I think this ML this
Okamo ML is just amazing. Okay. Uh so
I'm kind of still stuck learning F. I
kind of pissed at myself because
because with all the technology and AI
to help me I'm kind of very slow now
because when if if I was thinking when I
was a teen I was going to like I'm going
to learn the whole thing in one in one
day you know doesn't matter I don't
sleep I don't eat I'm just going to read
the F documentation from cover to cover
continuously until I finish it you know
I I I'll master the the in one
week. That was what I used to be when I
was younger. But now is I've been I've
been like oh learning uh F for for for
like a year
but still not doing much. I should have
anyway. So I don't feel too happy about
that. Um so let's see the comments.
Okay. By by the time you I'm reading the
comments you guys are you guys still
here? How many people?
14. Oh, I got 14 people. Amazing.
Okay. Random chat about programming
languages. Okay. So, let's see what what
comments. Okay. Uh
let's begin from the beginning. Okay.
So, what F. Yes. Fantastic. What is your
channel about? Kim about random. Okay.
Uh you Okay. You don't know me. Came
about you by random YouTube
recommendation. [laughter]
It's interesting that you YouTube
recommends me. Currently working as ML
computer vision. Oh, your ML means
machine learning and robotics. Okay. So,
what is my channel about? You just have
to watch and find out. In fact, what
you've seen today, if you are still
here, is is basically what my channel is
about. I'm kind of this weird, you might
say, coder, a nerd, a extreme case. And
I'm into programming languages. I'm into
math. And my opinions are usually not
the mainstream because I have kind of
weird life, okay, situations. So, what
is my channel about? Well, this is, you
know, you are seeing it. You are seeing
it. So I so I talked for half an hour
already 40 minutes. Okay. Previously I
was engaged in competitive programming
as a student. Seems you know a lot.
Fantastic.
I'm not a great coder. I don't code fast
actually. So like one of the things I
talk about is I'm I'm more of a thinker.
Okay. I like I like to think about
things design.
Uh not not a fast coder for sure. F is
very good. FSI fantastic. What is Lisp?
Just trying to learn. Okay, that's okay.
Well, that's that's a long story. Where
do I start? My 800 videos by by now I
have 800 videos. Today's episode 810.
Half of it is about lisp. Okay.
[laughter] So, you ask me what's a lisp?
I don't know. I don't know what's a
lisp. Okay. I call lisp. Okay. I I
called this basically all my life for
the past uh you know if if you count
Wufam language then for for the past 30
years if you exclude Wuam language then
I coded eag for the past 15 years every
day well actually by now 20 years
beginning in 2006
so by now I've code I'm coding emacisp
for 20 Yes. So, let me show you some
Emacs this code. So, this is my most
famous project keys 4,000 lines of code
and uh so that's key binding system.
That's the most efficient key binding
system for Emacs with all the keyboard
layout. You are seeing quy and uh
QFM
and you know different Norman and Mini
Mac and whole Mac. Anyway, so this is
list code. Okay, so and there's a lot
more. So you can see all my packages.
So I code lisp for like 20 30 years.
Okay. So
yeah so lisp is a big family. So in
origin you know you you know in the
beginning you got list then you got
several you got so many then then
basically today the major ones are
common this scheme this or known as
racket common scheme this enclosure
which is you may heard of it of it on
the Java platform JVM closure and emac
emac this is just for the emac text
editor okay
uh So well
yeah so there's another language which I
think is great that's Julia and very
interestingly Julia
is dynamic typed it's not static like
like the you know like like or camo
fascal
Julia is actually dynamically typed
so
but the thing you see this one Julia
programming language. But the thing is
that the Julia claims to be the fastest.
Okay. So, close to C faster than F or
camel
or uh Hascal or C++.
Okay. Judia very you know but it's
dynamically typed. It's not static. So
that's very interesting as I don't
understand. So
there are so many so much things to
learn. So how is it possible for a
dynamically typed programming language
to have to be even faster than let's say
C++?
That's what they claim anyway. They used
to have a uh like [snorts]
like that the the claim to fame is is
how fast they are. Okay. This this Julia
is invented about uh 10 or 15 years ago.
Okay. They used to have like a chart
showing how fast it is. Uh anyway, so
that's one of the things I want to
learn. Oh yeah. So the so but
you know you got so many so many so many
programming languages today more and
more and also um so you can't you don't
have time to learn them all. But also
um you see so one thing interesting
which brought me uh to rust is that you
see I was saying I I'm into functional
programming okay that is what interests
me the most not lisp you know some
people think I'm a lisp yeah I like lisp
but it's not about the parenthesis that
I love
nor is it about this maros in fact this
maros I despise is
what I love is the functional
programming aspect. Okay, functional.
So I don't like the imperative like all
the C, C++,
Pearl, Java, Python, this idiots, okay?
Like ugly you know,
functional programming is what I love.
Okay? So but I so that's why I'm so so I
want to learn functional programming.
But you see of all the functional
programming counting this common disp
and also if you count Hascal you count
Julia you count or camel you count ML
SML camel F you count all the users of
functional programming together
they are less than 1% of Rust okay so
that is what is interesting. You see,
that's a that that really got me
interested in Rust. You see, actually, I
talked about it um in my last video or
two. Okay. So, that's that got me really
interested in Rust.
So, I that's why I installed it and uh
plan to learn. Who knows? But who long
knows how long I'm going to learn it.
But, you know, so that's very
interesting. Rust is basically uh kind
of Okamo, you know, kind of the family.
So anyway, so uh
okay, we end up talking a lot. I end up
not doing what I wanted to do today, but
as usual, that's my talk show. I wanted
to actually do something for myself, but
uh Okay. So, so there's Julia. Okay,
that's my opinion. Uh, a lot of
companies use it. Okay, Closure is nice,
but F can compile to native code thanks
to native AOT. I don't know about that.
Julia is probably the best land. Um, you
see, one of the problem with the best
line is that they don't have users. So,
we when you don't have user, it's a
chronic problem like the skim disposis.
We fans wanted it to become popular like
since 20 years ago, 25 years ago, since
you, you know, as far as I know, since
year 2000, you know, oh, we heard, oh,
MIT started to have a course teaching
scheme as the first programming
language. We are all so happy back, you
know, 25 years ago. Finally, this is,
you know, taking the, you know, having
popularity, you know, taught in school
instead of Java. But then then it went
away. You see so skim this is supposed
to be the most buildable but but
actually it's not as I learned more. So
you see you don't you don't have users
and you don't want your users to be this
oh we love language but we are just we
don't do nothing. We just academic type
of people. That goes nowhere. You want
something that's used by Google in the
industry where people can find a job
like Rust. Okay? You don't want, oh, I
like scheme. I like Pascal. Nobody ever
your you and your friends are using it
but going nowhere for 30 years. That's a
case for Skim this and Hascal. Hascal is
pretty old by now. 30 years old,
you know. Yeah. very nice but no no no
users what the you going to do kind
of sad okay anyway anyway well not it's
just you know you have to just know how
things work in the world you can still
be your expert of Hascal you know and or
focus on academic research if that's
your thing that's good you know academic
research skill is still uh very uh used
in that field but us you know but in the
industry
not too much but well since like 15
years ago Facebook you know they they
use Hascal but still very small okay not
like compared to C++ or C or Goland or C
or Java they are the you know they they
hold the industry you know they you get
you get job and now rust Okay. So that's
that's a big consideration when you like
want to learn a language. So Julia is
somewhat disappointing. 10 years ago, oh
there's Julia, it's even faster sometime
than than C++ and it's functional.
Fantastic. A a lot of people I know tell
me about it. But but now 15 years has
passed. Where's Julia? Not much. Can you
find a job? Can you get a job in Julia?
Maybe [laughter]
you know kind of like that. So the
programming language popularity is
is important in some way. Okay. You know
depends on your
closure. So you know closure there are
also some you know some corporate use.
Um,
is there a reason you would use Julia's
chemistry student? So, Julia, let me
tell you guys, Julia is very kind of
popular in machine learning, machine
learning community and sciences. Okay?
So, it's kind of like in the same it's
like today's Python kind of, you know,
Python today is very much in machine
learning and sciences. Why is it?
Because Python was is a great
programming language? No, Python is one
of the circus Okay, but so but why
is Python so popular? Oh, numpy. Oh,
sci-fi. Oh, oh, the pi, you
know, pi. Because of Google.
Google happens to use Python because 25
years ago, 1999, there was Pearl, which
is The only alternative as a
screen language is Python. So they
picked Python and Google became you know
the greatest empire on earth. So and
they started to do data mining machine
learning since like 15 years ago. So
they turn out Python libraries and
everyone is like oh Google machine oh AI
AI chips oh you know so Python
became popular.
Is it because it's good? No. Python is
worst one of the worst.
So, Julia is is very uh kind of popular
kind of in the machine learning and
mathematics scientific computation.
Okay, that's that's basically my area
Julia but I but but I can't you know I
decided I want to uh first learn F# uh
because you got to do one thing at a
time. The other reason I'm learning F#
instead of Julia is that so F# and O
camel they are they have the background
uh proof system proof system and type
theory okay that's what I really want to
know a lot more so proof theory of
mathematics okay so for example okamo
okamo f and then there's a h there is
you know the cq there is um I mean
a lot of them are written or camel okay
so you know that again that type
inference system so if you really so I
recommend if you are into math if you
into the branch of logic that's proof
systems and proof theory or category
theory you want to know or camel f okay
you want to kind of and ling okay ling
Ling is written uh originally also camel
but I think they I think they switched
to C++ first. I for I forgot maybe.
So anyway,
so I think that's it for today. I talked
about Lua when you mentioned Julia. I
thought about Lua Julia's main problem
is not enough adoption. That's correct.
But he has the best design so far.
That's what I heard.
Uh so so many messages. I don't remember
who each one of you guys are. Honestly,
I haven't previously heard of Julia. I
did my high school thesis.
Oh, Lativia high school thesis in C++
which was a C++ simulation for physics.
Okay, I have used Lua to teach my
sister. So, Lua is another language that
happens to be very fast. So, I was a bit
puzzled what you know I asked AI about
three years ago. So, how you know
usually dynamic languages are slower
because you know because when you have
statically typed the compiler knows what
type. So, you don't have to check what
type some value is when you run it.
But but Lui you know is very fast. So
what so I asked one one of the reason
turns out is that because Lua is
actually pretty small. Lua is pretty
small language. When you are very small
like you don't have much different
construct or data structures built in
you can be more faster because you you
have less things to worry about. So
anyway, so
so what one one of the question I do not
fully I do not understand is what kind
of features what kind of thing that
makes a programming language fast
you know I don't know so for example
statically typed versus dynamic
dynamically typed we typically think you
know statically type is faster for sure
but Lua and Julia
are exceptions you see. So in the case
of Lua I also know well because it's a
tiny language. So but then what what
made Julia so fast? What what you know
what what magic do they have? I don't
know. I don't really know. So I asked AI
but I don't I still don't fully
understand. Um,
[sighs and gasps]
Julia is not primarily a functional
programming language and does not
compile to native AOT. Oh, okay. I don't
know. Julia always needs a runtime. Is
that true? H.
Okay. I don't Well, maybe you are right.
You're probably right, but I don't know.
Uh,
okay. I think that's it for today.
Uh, I think I've used wufam in
university as math solver. Yes, a lot of
people do that.
Um
I mean that's the original kind of the
foundational use of wuam language to
solve equations, integrals, derivatives,
differential equations used in
engineering a lot.
Uh
Julia uh Julia okay net C++ uh C and F
needs runtime
just in time like Java closure Julia but
can bypass this?
Okay. Uh
is operating system important in your
daily computer use? I always use Windows
but as soon as I had to work in robotics
with RO OS had to go with Linux. Yeah.
Okay. I think that's it.
Anything else guys? So
who uh you know you guys watching me why
are you here?
uh Google recommendation. That's
interesting. But I don't have much
viewers, you know. I have maybe 7,000
followers, but
it will be the day when Google recommend
me because I'm not, you know, doing the
those promotions and stuff.
Uh,
okay. Anything else, guys?
Link to Discord.
Uh you go to my website kasali.org I
mean kasali.info
info or just search for you'll find it.
X a h e search. So you go to my website
then you scroll down then there is a
link to my discord. Click on you know
then you get you go to it. Okay that's
my discord.
uh we it's not as popular as before like
uh you know so we still have some people
but anyway
okay so let me think what to do now so
either I can um
code something to finish what I want to
do today
talk show okay let me let me continue to
code. Okay. So, how long have we been?
54 minutes. Okay. Let me just so you
guys can leave if you are, you know,
need something to do. Anyway, but I'm
going to continue. Okay. So, this is uh
guac answer how to call shell command in
F. Okay. So, I'm just going to copy
that.
Uh I'm just going to
Create
a new section.
Copy my question.
TBU to create a bubble style show in
browser. So you got a bubble. Then go
back to here then copy the entire
article. Okay. So go down. So copy it.
That's cop copied in markdown. So new
buffer paste. So here is the AI answer
together 150 lines. Okay. Select all
press a key. They became HTML. So the AI
output is marked down. So now they
become HTML because of my Emacs command
magic. Okay. So you can see all the
commands in the ping window. That's that
was HTML markdown to HTML by Python.
I believe we coded that live several
months ago. Okay. Or or maybe last year.
So anyway, cut it. Close it. Paste here.
Show in browser. So we have grabbed the
entire AI answer here. How to call shell
command in F. Okay. So we're going to
read it carefully. So I have a copy of
the AI output.
Amazing. So uh so it says well
it says basically you need to do this.
Okay so let me try it. uh you know it's
kind of painful because you know in in
pearl
if you want to call shell command it's
just one line qx qx parn then whatever
shell like ls- a or whatever you know qx
parenthesis then ls then you get it I I
can run it okay so
uh I can show you different programming
languages how they call shell because
call shell command is one of the things
I do often for my stuff. So for example
create a new section
a new pearl code pearl pop it out then
qx that is the function then let's just
say ls well
uh you don't you I you know I'm on
windows so I don't think you have ls but
let's just run it and see what happens I
forgot
ls is not recognized as internal
external internal command. That's
because I'm on Windows. So on Windows
PowerShell, you need to do the let's
write complete. Okay. No output. So you
need to print. Uh so how do you print in
Pearl? I don't remember. So maybe that.
Okay. Print. Let's try.
There it is. Can you see?
So you see it the pearl code calls the
shell the command and and get you know
get the output. You see that's how
simple it is. Uh
call shell command. Okay let me magnify.
Okay that's how you do it in show in
browser there. And in Python it's more
complex. you you need 10 lines. Okay? Uh
in fact, I have you know it's all in my
tutorials. Let's go to my tutorials
in Python. How do you call shell
command? You have
uh
shell. Okay. Search. No. What
uh Python tutorial? So wait
closure decorator class object id and
type import modules
shell command uh work directory find
script path
uh why can system call. Okay I should
add
okay should system call. So in Python
this is what you do for three lines it
used to be 10 it used to be uh more
lines
you know it used to be more but you see
compare
Python three lines versus the pearl
uh where is the pearl one line okay now
in eacis I can show you in eac this uh
but I can also show you you know I can
show you in goland in eacis but Anyway,
but we want to do in in uh in
PowerShell. Okay, I mean not PowerShell,
in u in F. So, how do you do in F? I
don't know. Let's try.
Uh so, start a new F. Okay. So, pop it
out. And the AI says do this. Okay.
Paste it. Okay. Now, Jesus.
[laughter]
Oh my god. to to call a shell command
you need all these um execute process.
Oh god, you have to define yourself.
Uh I don't like it.
But where is the shell command? So where
so where is the actual shell command
usage? Oh god. So copy that.
So can I run? Let's run this first. Can
I just run this? Is it valid? Yes, it's
valid. Amazing AI just generate code.
Okay. Now go to the bottom. Then you say
this is how you use it.
So execute process uptime P. No, that's
not a windows there. So wait. So you got
a Windows here. result equals to
command.exe
C the
so what is this doing? Uh
what
can we change it? Yeah, let's try change
it. Okay, let's just say the
uh
duh. Okay.
Then it prints exit code stand out. Then
if if something something something.
Okay. Let's try run.
Oh god. Type constraint mismatch. The
type process is not compatible with uh
string process. Okay. I don't
understand.
Okay. Do we have uh F# expert here?
Oh, fast FW says the two lines of Pearl
and three lines of Python are not
crossplatform.
Uh I I'm pretty sure they are.
So he says F code can be crossplatform
easily.
What do you mean they are not co
platform? Okay, there's I think there's
two questions. I mean when you say call
shell command one meaning is that it
actually call shell
like on Windows it would call powershell
or command exe then the power the shell
actually call whatever command you want
to call such as the okay so for example
our pearl code
our pearl code call the but I believe it
actually call shells So it I mean it
calls the command exe then the command
execute that. So I think that's maybe
that's what you mean. Yeah. Uh yes I
think so but you are say so on on the
other hand
in all these languages you can also call
a external command but without starting
a shell you know without like relying a
shell to do it which is in general
faster more efficient. I well how do I
know because
because if you go to my Emacs tutorial
then you'll see
the two different ways for example so
Emac lisp there you got introduction to
lisp this basics or then you got emacisp
then you got so you want to call
external command core shell command so
there are several variations the
simplest
is just this single line shell command
command you know whatever duh or date or
whatever that's it okay this eac this
you know so on windows you can just call
date you know on on you know on Linux
you can call ls
uh on Mac you can mac is zshell which is
bash compatible anyway the bottom line
is just single line but they rely they
actually call the shell the shell
actually execute whatever the shell
command. Okay, that's one way.
But
you know and then you can have
variations of you know just
get the string output or or wait for it
to finish or don't wait for it to finish
you know but then another way more
efficient is you start a external
process. So this way you you skipped you
skip starting the shell may it be bash
command.exe exe or zshell whatever you
skip it you call the external command
name directly
so all the argument you don't you don't
need to escape it like in shell escape
very complicated so but so you got this
but this is actually uh five lines of
code actually more in practice usually
ends up like 10 10 20 lines of code and
uh fairly difficult to understand
Because because then you have to think
about like the standard out the standard
arrow and you have a you have to have a
sentinel to know when it finish
something like that and you need a
output buffer you have to specify where
does output goes and so on. Okay. So so
this is more complicated but the same
idea applies in all I believe all
languages. You can either just call the
shell let the shell start you know bash
or whatever which is one line very easy
but or you can have you know this
you know start external program core
process
uh which is more comp complicated okay
so I believe so this this pearl qx I
believe that's just core shell but so
this
apparent so obviously this F is actually
calling external command but using the
system library which I I don't
understand F. Okay.
So anyway, so right now we got an error
and I don't understand I don't know how
to fix. So
okay and
net API. Okay. So, uh so
so fast forward says what do you you do
not need directory API.
Okay. Command exe might be needed in F.
You do not call system process but use
the net API. Okay. ANET developer will
use a net API for that. not calling
external process. Okay. Okay. That I
guess that's a different way. Calling
external process is not crossplatform.
Net used for its crossplatform
capability. Why people use net? I'm not
sure about that because for example that
EMAC this code I showed that works
crossplatform on Windows on Linux on Mac
because I've run them in all um
but I think I I
but so what do you mean exactly? I'm not
too clear.
Uh, Python has problem with uh, god this
annoying like every time you click on
this window
it generates this uh, like every time
you click
wait. Yeah, you every time you click it
generates like a right click. Very
annoying.
God.
Uh, calling external process. Okay. Uh,
Python I don't quite understand. Python
has problem with multi-processing as
multiprocessing is only li that actually
does it.
Oh, okay. I don't know.
Right. Uh, get files. Yeah, I've I know
that one. I seen that. But what I need
is not just get list of files. What I
need is actually I need to
uh
you know so so so a month ago or so we
did
talk about images especially display P3
like we have this fancy image formats
HIC AVIF JPEG XL that supports colors
outside of the normal
um the normal
sRGB. So it's called white gamut colors.
Okay,
very interesting. So anyway, so one of
the thing is you got uh webp okay not
related to that but you got webp image
format which is much smaller than JPEG
or PNG.
So I have you know
tens of thousand JPEG files and PNG. I
need to convert it. I can trivially do
it in eacisp which I've been coding for
20 years. I can I can start right now or
finish in 10 minutes, you know. But so
but I want to learn F. So I need to have
F worker directory get get all the PNG
files or JPEG and call shell command.
Call this cp command. Okay.
So this command will be called thousands
of times like 10,000 something
you know. So so that's why I'm you know
that's why I'm starting you know asking
the question like I want to learn from
the most the the most basic part part is
how do you call a shell command you know
instead of asking AI to just write this
whole for me I want to know like the
basics how to call a shell command. So
that's what I'm doing this for. Anyway,
I think that's it. Um,
hi long time reader. Uh, new viewer. Oh,
uh, thank you Persia.
Okay. Um, yeah, it's been over an hour.
I think that's it. Okay.
Okay. Typical Fdev will look for a net
lib that converts. Oh.
>> [laughter]
>> That's so that's so you are introducing
me new methods which I'm not familiar.
So my typical way is always just
from from like Unix languages. I just
called a shell command because this webp
is this webp command is very standard
for converting you know webps from
Google. So they provided this CEP
command to convert PNG or JPEG to
to WEBP format saves you like onethird
of the file size.
So but you are saying you know if but if
I you know switch to the Microsoft.NET
net away.
I I don't know about that because
usually from my experience,
you know,
I'm not sure. I don't I don't think I
have a good experience because anyway,
first of all, if you switch to net find
a library to convert webp, first of all,
the algorithm is different from the
official webp, you know, because this is
Google's, you know, tool. But if you
switch the net implementation
the result is not exactly the same which
is you know you can still trust it but I
don't but requires
kind of you know you you need to look
into so that's one thing the result is
different from
Google's official CP program.
Uh the other thing then is from my
experience I not sure I trust um maybe I
should but I don't know net or Microsoft
stuff much but I know for example one
thing I need to do is to find the image
width and height.
So how do you find image width and
height? I have looked into you know in
you can use image magic, you can use
python uh called uh the pillow library
or something the python image library
you can use
you know and on a Mac you have the zip
program
built on built in on Mac come with a
Mac. Okay. Where is it? SIP
uh
what
there okay Mac OS you have the SIP
program that can show the width and
height of image native very fast image
magic is classic but it's kind of
bloated then um but so the question is
on Windows
what is a native way to get image files
width and height without installing
anything extra. I looked into that. So
there is PowerShell. Okay.
So what you do is so let's search okay
image with okay so you got EAC this can
do that but but it's got a bug. Okay.
You got EMAC this way. You got Goland
can do that. Then you got PowerShell.
You got Python and you got image magic
and you got the zip mac on the Mac.
Okay. So, but if you look so eag it's
got a perk. Okay. So, if you you can
read my page I got details. Okay.
But then Golan very fast. Okay. You can
do it this way. Okay. So JPEG I don't
know if it supports uh PNG or WP. So
this code only support JPEG.
So PowerShell. So what one of the way is
PowerShell? Actually I got the answer
from AI. But this is very slow. Okay.
This PowerShell creates you know like
the net system.drawing
image you know it's some kind of net
stuff. I don't I don't understand. But
this is like slow slow as hell.
So I don't have a good impression and I
asked AI before you know like on on
Windows what's a you know easy way to
find the images width and height using
net you know supposedly net is this all
powerful engine but [laughter] but I
can't find a way on the Mac you have the
sips command line built in on Linux
usually you you can use actually ident
identify or file uh which one file
that can also output width and height of
a image
native very fast and you can install
image magic. But but on Windows this
like
how do you do that
ABI? Okay. Yeah. Then you get into C++
first which is a hell. I don't I don't I
don't know nothing about
why F in 2026. My entire 1 hour video
today was talking about that. I think
you were late.
Okay, I think that's it. Bye guys.
Bye for real. It's uh right now it's uh
okay 70 80 minutes.
So fast forward
my question how do you find the image
width and height
in with a net I mean net is supposed to
be this huge and powerful engine right
like Java
but why is it I can't have a easy way
to get the width and height of a image
and also I you know it would be nice if
I can have that for JPEG and PNG and
webp
like I I I I I asked AI before like a
year ago and it did give me answers like
oh yeah I think I remember it it
mentioned this ski shop. I think I
remembered that it mentioned something
like that like like that but then I have
to like I have to install it right like
I mean so my question is how do I do it
like how how to that you know [laughter]
I don't want to spend like two hours to
then to realize oh that that's how you
see yeah it's a GitHub
ski crossplatform.net NET graphics
libraries. So I'm not at a level where I
want to install
.NET libraries yet. I want to be able to
just actually I'm still learning .NET
like like recently, you know, I'm not at
a level to actually install anything
net libraries yet,
but I find it, you know, kind of odd to
get image width and height. you need to
install this you know a library where on
on a Mac and on Linux
you can have built in you know programs
that does it so that's so that that is
my kind of my impression not good
impression
you see
ski shop is a net wrapper around
Google's powerful ski graphics engine.
Okay. I haven't heard of Google Skia
graphics engine. Where does it come? So,
Google.
So, uh it enables developers to create
2D graphics including shapes. Okay. So,
what about what is this Google? But why
is you know imagine to get the image
width and height. Why why net can do
that? I thought you know supposed to be
should be pretty basic, right? Isn't it?
Okay. So, Skia
is a 2D graphics library.
Yeah. Okay. So, from Google.
I didn't know.
Written in C++.
You know, there there's a little
friction there. I don't I don't want
anything that has the name C++ in it.
C++.
Skia Skia. Okay. So, Skia abstract away
platform specific. So, what is this?
Open-source 2D graphics library. Okay.
So, from Skia and Google
bought it in 2005.
Okay.
Anyway, bye guys.
No. Okay. So, yeah. Okay. One thing at a
time. Eventually, I'll get to that.
Bye.